<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
(using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<!--  ?rfc subcompact="no" ?  -->
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!--
==================================== 80 ========================================
==================================== 72 ================================
-->
<!--            TODO!!
- Summarize RFC 4389
- Summarize draft-chakrabarti-nordmark-6man-efficient-nd-07
"IPv6 Neighbor Discovery Optimizations for Wired and Wireless Networks"
- [?perhaps doubtful?] Cite and summarize RFC 5757
... respond to Thomas Schmidt <t.schmidt@haw-hamburg.de>
... on the premise that multicast makes things difficult in
different way...?

-->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-perkins-intarea-multicast-ieee802-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Multicast Over IEEE 802 Wireless">Multicast Considerations
    over IEEE 802 Wireless Media</title>

    <author fullname="Charles E. Perkins" initials="C.E." surname="Perkins">
      <organization abbrev="Futurewei">Futurewei Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <code>95050</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1-408-330-4586</phone>

        <email>charliep@computer.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dorothy Stanley" initials="D" surname="Stanley">
      <organization abbrev="HPE">Hewlett Packard Enterprise</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2000 North Naperville Rd.</street>

          <city>Naperville</city>

          <code>60566</code>

          <region>IL</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 630 979 1572</phone>

        <email>dstanley@arubanetworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W" surname="Kumari">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Juan Carlos Zuniga" initials="JC" surname="Zuniga">
      <organization abbrev="SIGFOX">SIGFOX</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>425 rue Jean Rostand</street>

          <city>Labege</city>

          <code>31670</code>

          <region/>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>j.c.zuniga@ieee.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="14" month="September" year="2016"/>

    <!-- day="25" month="October" year="2010" /> -->

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Area</workgroup>

    <keyword>Multicast</keyword>

    <keyword>IEEE 802 Wireless Multicast</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes some performance issues that have been
      observed when multicast packet transmission is attempted over IEEE 802
      wireless media. Multicast features specified for IEEE 802 wireless media
      related to multicast are also described, along with explanations about
      how these features can help ameliorate the observed performance issues.
      IETF protocols that are likely to be affected by the observed
      performance issues are identified, and workarounds are proposed in some
      cases. The performance of multicast over wireless media often can be
      quite different than the performance of unicast. This draft describes
      the nature of the differences and the effects on representative IETF
      protocols. We also describe some efforts that have been made by IEEE 802
      Wireless groups to ameliorate the performance differences.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Many IETF protocol designs depend upon multicast or broadcast for
      delivery of control messages to multiple receivers. Multicast is used
      for various purposes such as neighborhood discovery, network flooding,
      address resolution, as well as reduction in media access for data
      traffic.</t>

      <t>IETF protocols typically rely on network protocol layering in order
      to reduce or eliminate any dependence of higher level protocols on the
      specific nature of the MAC layer protocols or the physical media. In the
      case of multicast transmission, higher level protocols may be designed
      as if transmitting a packet to an IP address has the same cost in
      interference and network media access, regardless of whether the
      destination IP address is a unicast address or a multicast or broadcast
      address. This model of operation was reasonable for networks where the
      physical medium was like an Ethernet.</t>

      <t>Unfortunately, for many wireless media, the costs can be quite
      different. It is the purpose of this Internet Draft to identify the ways
      in which the costs can be different. Using this information, we then
      proceed to identify some possible effects on the actual operation of
      IETF protocols over wireless media.</t>

      <t>IEEE 802 Wireless working groups, especially 802.11, have made a
      number of attempts to improve the performance of multicast transmissions
      at Layer 2. In this draft we also include a description of some of these
      efforts. This information is closely related to material presented at
      IETF 94 [cite 11-15-1261-03]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="def" title="Terminology">
      <!--
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>

        <t>This document also uses some terminology from <xref
        target="RFC5444" />.</t>
        -->

      <t>This document uses the following definitions:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="AP"><vspace/> IEEE 802.11 Access Point.</t>

          <t><vspace/></t>

          <t hangText="STA"><vspace/> IEEE 802.11 station.</t>

          <t><vspace/></t>

          <t hangText="basic rate"><vspace/> a "lowest common denominator"
          rate at which multicast and broadcast traffic is generally
          transmitted.</t>

          <t><vspace/></t>

          <t hangText="MCS"><vspace/> Modulation and Coding Scheme.</t>

          <t><vspace/></t>
        </list></t>

      <!-- <t><vspace blankLines="19" /></t>  -->
    </section>

    <section anchor="layer2" title="Identified Issues at Layer 2">
      <t>In this section we list some of the issues arising at Layer 2
      surrounding the use of multicast in IETF protocols over wireless
      media.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Multicast traffic is typically much less reliable than unicast
          traffic.</t>

          <t>Multicast / broadcast traffic is generally sent at a lowest
          common denominator rate, known as a basic rate. This might be as low
          as 6 Mbps, when unicast links are operating at 600 Mbps.
          Transmission at a lower rate requires more occupancy of the wireless
          medium and thus less airtime for everything else.</t>

          <t>Wireless multicast affects wired LANs because the AP extends the
          wired segment. <list style="symbols">
              <t>All broadcast frames on LAN side are copied to WLAN.</t>

              <t>In WLAN, broadcast messages transmitted at most robust
              MCS.</t>

              <t>Most robust MCS implies large frames sent at slow rate.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Multicast can work poorly with the power-save mechanisms in
          802.11. <list style="symbols">
              <t>Both unicast and multicast traffic can be delayed by
              power-saving mechanisms.</t>

              <t>Unicast is delayed until a STA wakes up and asks for it.
              Additionally, unicast traffic may be delayed to improve power
              save, efficiency and increase probability of aggregation.</t>

              <t>Multicast traffic is delayed in a wireless network if any of
              the STAs in that network are power savers. All STAs have to be
              awake at a known time to receive multicast traffic.</t>

              <t>Packets can also be discarded due to buffer limitations in
              the AP and non-AP STA.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ietf-effects"
             title="Some Possible Effects on Representative IETF protocols">
      <t>In this section we list some of the issues arising at layer 3
      surrounding the use of multicast in IETF protocols over wireless media.
      We mention a few representative IETF protocols, and describe some
      possible effects due to performance degradation when using multicast
      transmissions for control messages. Common uses include: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Control plane for IPv4 and IPv6</t>

          <t>ARP and Neighbor Discovery</t>

          <t>Service discovery</t>

          <t>Applications (video delivery, stock data etc)</t>

          <t>Other L3 protocols (non-IP)</t>
        </list></t>

      <section anchor="IPv4" title="IPv4 uses">
        <t>The following list contains a few representative IPv4 protocols
        using multicast. <list style="symbols">
            <t>ARP</t>

            <t>DHCP</t>

            <t>mDNS</t>
          </list> After initial configuration, ARP and DHCP occur much less
        commonly.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'IPv4 uses' -->

      <section anchor="IPv6" title="IPv6 uses">
        <t>The following list contains a few representative IPv6 protocols
        using multicast. IPv6 makes much more extensive use of multicast.
        <list style="symbols">
            <t>DHCPv6</t>

            <t>Liveness detection (NUD)</t>

            <t>Some control plane protocols are not very tolerant of packet
            loss, especially neighbor discovery.</t>

            <t>Services may be considered lost if several consecutive packets
            fail.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Address Resolution</t>

        <t>Service Discovery</t>

        <t>Route Discovery</t>

        <t>Decentralized Address Assignment</t>

        <t>Geographic routing</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'IPv6 uses' -->

      <section anchor="mld" title="Disabling Multicast on WiFi">
        <t>Multicast Listener Discovery(MLD) <xref target="RFC4541"/> is often
        used to identify members of a multicast group that are connected to
        the ports of a switch. Forwarding multicast frames into a WiFi-enabled
        area can use such switch support for hardware forwarding state
        information. However, since IPv6 makes heavy use of multicast, each
        STA with an IPv6 address will require state on the switch for several
        and possibly many multicast solicited-node addresses. Multicast
        addresses that do not have forwarding state installed (perhaps due to
        hardware memory limitations on the switch) cause frames to be flooded
        on all ports of the switch.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'Disabling Multicast on WiFi' -->

      <section anchor="spurious" title="Spurious Neighbor Discovery">
        <t>On the Internet there is a "background radiation" of scanning
        traffic (people scanning for vulnerable machines) and backscatter
        (responses from spoofed traffic, etc). This means that the router is
        constantly getting packets destined for machines whose IP addresses
        may or may not be in use. In the cases where the IP is assigned to a
        machine, the router broadcasts an ARP request, gets back an ARP reply,
        caches this and then can deliver traffic to the host. In the cases
        where the IP address is not in use, the router broadcasts one (or
        more) ARP requests, and never gets a reply. This means that it does
        not populate the ARP cache, and the next time there is traffic for
        that IP address it will broadcast ARP requests again. The rate of
        these ARP requests is proportional to the size of the subnets, the
        rate of scanning and backscatter, and how long the router keeps state
        on non-responding ARPs. As it turns out, this rate is inversely
        proportional to how occupied the subnet is (valid ARPs end up in a
        cache, stopping the broadcasting; unused IPs never respond, and so
        cause more broadcasts). Depending on the address space in use, the
        time of day, how occupied the subnet is, and other unknown factors, on
        the order of 2000 broadcasts per second have been observed at the IETF
        NOCs.</t>

        <t>On a wired network, there is not a huge difference amongst unicast,
        multicast and broadcast traffic; but this is not true in the wireless
        realm. Wireless equipment often is unable to send this amount of
        broadcast and multicast traffic. Consequently, on the wireless
        networks, we observe a significant amount of dropped broadcast and
        multicast packets. This, in turn, means that when a host connects it
        is often not able to complete DHCP, and IPv6 RAs get dropped, leading
        to users being unable to use the network.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'layer3' title='Spurious Neighbor Discovery' -->
    </section>

    <!-- 'Some Possible Effects on Representative IETF protocols' -->

    <section anchor="optim2" title="Layer 2 optimizations">
      <t>This section lists some optimizations that have been specified for
      use with 802.11 that are aimed at reducing or eliminating the causes of
      performance loss discussed in <xref target="layer2"/>.</t>

      <section anchor="proxy-arp" title="Proxy ARP in 802.11-2012">
        <t>The AP knows all associated STAs MAC address and IP address; in
        other words, the AP acts as the central "manager" for all the 802.11
        STAs in its BSS. Proxy ARP is easy to implement at the AP, and offers
        the following advantages: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Reduced broadcast traffic (transmitted at low MCS) on the
            wireless medium</t>

            <t>STA benefits from extended power save in sleep mode, as ARP
            requests are replied to by AP.</t>

            <t>Keeps ARP frames off the wireless medium.</t>

            <t>Changes are not needed to STA implementation.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Here is the specification language from clause 10.23.13 in [2] as
        described in <xref target="dot11-proxyarp"/>: <list style="empty">
            <t>When the AP supports Proxy ARP "[...] the AP shall maintain a
            Hardware Address to Internet Address mapping for each associated
            station, and shall update the mapping when the Internet Address of
            the associated station changes. When the IPv4 address being
            resolved in the ARP request packet is used by a non-AP STA
            currently associated to the BSS, the proxy ARP service shall
            respond on behalf of the non-AP STA"</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="buffer" title="Buffering to improve Power-Save">
        <t>The AP acts on behalf of STAs in various ways. In order to improve
        the power-saving feature for STAs in its BSS, the AP buffers frames
        for delivery to the STA at the time when the STA is scheduled for
        reception.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'Buffering to improve Power-Save'  -->

      <section anchor="ipv6" title="IPv6 support in 802.11-2012">
        <t>IPv6 uses Neighbor Discovery Protocol (NDP) instead Every IPv6 node
        subscribes to special multicast address Neighbor-Solicitation message
        replaces ARP</t>

        <t>Here is the specification language from-10.23.13 in [2]: <list
            style="empty">
            <t>"When an IPv6 address is being resolved, the Proxy Neighbor
            Discovery service shall respond with a Neighbor Advertisement
            message [...] on behalf of an associated STA to an [ICMPv6]
            Neighbor Solicitation message [...]. When MAC address mappings
            change, the AP may send unsolicited Neighbor Advertisement
            Messages on behalf of a STA."</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>NDP may be used to request additional information <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Maximum Transmission Unit</t>

            <t>Router Solicitation</t>

            <t>Router Advertisement, etc.</t>
          </list> NDP messages are sent as group addressed (broadcast) frames
        in 802.11. Using the proxy operation helps to keep NDP messages off
        the wireless medium.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'IPv6 support in 802.11-2012' -->

      <section anchor="convert" title="Conversion of Multicast to Unicast">
        <t>It is often possible to transmit control and data messages by using
        unicast transmissions to each station individually.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'Conversion of Multicast to Unicast' -->

      <section anchor="DMS" title="Directed Multicast Service (DMS)">
        <t>There are situations where more is needed than simply converting
        multicast to unicast [citation needed]. For these purposes, DMS
        enables a client to request that the AP transmit multicast group
        addressed frames destined to the requesting clients as individually
        addressed frames [i.e., convert multicast to unicast]. <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>DMS Requires 802.11n A-MSDUs</t>

            <t>Individually addressed frames are acknowledged and are buffered
            for power save clients</t>

            <t>Requesting STA may specify traffic characteristics for DMS
            traffic</t>

            <t>DMS was defined in IEEE Std 802.11v-2011</t>
          </list> DMS is not currently implemented in products. DMS does
        require changes to both AP and STA implementation.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'Directed Multicast Service (DMS)' -->

      <section anchor="GCR" title="GroupCast with Retries (GCR)">
        <t>GCR (defined in <xref target="dot11aa"/>) provides greater
        reliability by using either unsolicited retries or a block
        acknowledgement mechanism. GCR increases probability of broadcast
        frame reception success, but still does not guarantee success.</t>

        <t>For the block acknowledgement mechanism, the AP transmits each
        group addressed frame as conventional group addressed transmission.
        Retransmissions are group addressed, but hidden from non-11aa clients.
        A directed block acknowledgement scheme is used to harvest reception
        status from receivers; retransmissions are based upon these
        responses.</t>

        <t>GCR is suitable for all group sizes including medium to large
        groups. As the number of devices in the group increases, GCR can send
        block acknowledgement requests to only a small subset of the group.
        GCR does require changes to both AP and STA implementation.</t>

        <t>GCR may introduce unacceptable latency. After sending a group of
        data frames to the group, the AP has do the following: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>unicast a Block Ack Request (BAR) to a subset of members.</t>

            <t>wait for the corresponding Block Ack (BA).</t>

            <t>retransmit any missed frames.</t>

            <t>resume other operations which may have been delayed.</t>
          </list> This latency may not be acceptable for some traffic.</t>

        <t>There are ongoing extensions in 802.11 to improve GCR performance.
        <list style="symbols">
            <t>BAR is sent using downlink MU-MIMO (note that downlink MU-MIMO
            is already specified in 802.11-REVmc 4.3).</t>

            <t>BA is sent using uplink MU-MIMO (which is a .11ax feature).</t>

            <t>Additional 802.11ax extensions are under consideration; see
            <xref target="mc-ack-mux"/></t>

            <t>Latency may also be reduced by simultaneously receiving BA
            information from multiple clients.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'GroupCast with Retries (GCR)' -->
    </section>

    <!-- 'Layer 2 optimizations' -->

    <section anchor="optim3"
             title="Higher Layer Optimizations and Mitigations">
      <t>This section lists some optimizations that have been specified for
      use with 802.11 that are aimed at reducing or eliminating the causes of
      performance loss discussed in section <xref target="optim3"/>.</t>

      <section anchor="mitigate-spurious"
               title="Mitigating Problems from Spurious Neighbor Discovery">
        <t><list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="ARP Sponges"><vspace blankLines="1"/> An ARP Sponge
            sits on a network and learn which IPs addresses are actually in
            use. It also listen for ARP requests, and, if it sees an ARP for
            an IP address which it believes is not used, it will reply with
            its own MAC address. This means that the router now has an IP to
            MAC mapping, which it caches. If that IP is later assigned to an
            machine (e.g using DHCP), the ARP sponge will see this, and will
            stop replying for that address. Gratuitous ARPs (or the machine
            ARPing for its gateway) will replace the sponged address in the
            router ARP table. This technique is quite effective; but,
            unfortunately, the ARP sponge daemons were not really designed for
            this use (the standard one <xref target="arpsponge"/>, was
            designed to deal with the disappearance of participants from an
            IXP) and so are not optimized for this purpose. We have to run one
            daemon per subnet, the tuning is tricky (the scanning rate versus
            the population rate versus retires, etc.) and sometimes the
            daemons just seem to stop, requiring a restart of the daemon and
            causing disruption. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

            <t hangText="Router mitigations"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Some
            routers (often those based on Linux) implement a "negative ARP
            cache" daemon. Simply put, if the router does not see a reply to
            an ARP it can be configured to cache this information for some
            interval. Unfortunately, the core routers which we are using do
            not support this. When a host connects to network and gets an IP
            address, it will ARP for its default gateway (the router). The
            router will update its cache with the IP to host MAC mapping
            learnt from the request (passive ARP learning). <vspace
            blankLines="1"/></t>

            <t hangText="Firewall unused space"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The
            distribution of users on wireless networks / subnets changes from
            meeting to meeting (e.g the "IETF-secure" SSID was renamed to
            "IETF", fewer users use "IETF-legacy", etc). This utilization is
            difficult to predict ahead of time, but we can monitor the usage
            as attendees use the different networks. By configuring multiple
            DHCP pools per subnet, and enabling them sequentially, we can have
            a large subnet, but only assign addresses from the lower portions
            of it. This means that we can apply input IP access lists, which
            deny traffic to the upper, unused portions. This means that the
            router does not attempt to forward packets to the unused portions
            of the subnets, and so does not ARP for it. This method has proven
            to be very effective, but is somewhat of a blunt axe, is fairly
            labor intensive, and requires coordination. <vspace
            blankLines="1"/></t>

            <t hangText="Disabling/filtering ARP requests"><vspace
            blankLines="1"/> In general, the router does not need to ARP for
            hosts; when a host connects, the router can learn the IP to MAC
            mapping from the ARP request sent by that host. This means that we
            should be able to disable and / or filter ARP requests from the
            router. Unfortunately, ARP is a very low level / fundamental part
            of the IP stack, and is often offloaded from the normal control
            plane. While many routers can filter layer-2 traffic, this is
            usually implemented as an input filter and / or has limited
            ability to filter output broadcast traffic. This means that the
            simple "just disable ARP or filter it outbound" seems like a
            really simple (and obvious) solution, but implementations /
            architectural issues make this difficult or awkward in practice.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

            <t hangText="NAT"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The broadcasts are
            overwhelmingly being caused by outside scanning / backscatter
            traffic. This means that, if we were to NAT the entire (or a large
            portion) of the attendee networks, there would be no NAT
            translation entries for unused addresses, and so the router would
            never ARP for them. The IETF NOC has discussed NATing the entire
            (or large portions) attendee address space, but a: elegance and b:
            flaming torches and pitchfork concerns means we have not attempted
            this yet. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

            <t hangText="Stateful firewalls"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Another
            obvious solution would be to put a stateful firewall between the
            wireless network and the Internet. This firewall would block
            incoming traffic not associated with an outbound request. The IETF
            philosophy has been to have the network as open as possible /
            honor the end-to-end principle. An attendee on the meeting network
            should be an Internet host, and should be able to receive
            unsolicited requests. Unfortunately, keeping the network working
            and stable is the first priority and a stateful firewall may be
            required in order to achieve this.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <!-- 'Mitigating Problems from Spurious Neighbor Discovery' -->
    </section>

    <!-- 'Layer 3 optimizations' -->

    <section anchor="other-media"
             title="Multicast Considerations for Other Wireless Media">
      <t>Many of the causes of performance degradation described in earlier
      sections are also observable for wireless media other than 802.11.</t>

      <t>For instance, problems with power save, excess media occupancy, and
      poor reliability will also affect 802.15.3 and 802.15.4. However, 802.15
      media specifications do not include similar mechanisms of the type that
      have been developed for 802.11. In fact, the design philosophy for
      802.15 is more oriented towards minimality, with the result that many
      such functions would more likely be relegated to operation within higher
      layer protocols. This leads to a patchwork of non-interoperable and
      vendor-specific solutions. See <xref target="uli"/> for some additional
      discussion, and a proposal for a task group to resolve similar issues,
      in which the multicast problems might be considered for mitigation.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- 'Multicast Considerations for Other Wireless Media' -->

    <section anchor="sec" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce any security mechanisms, and does
      not have any impact on existing security mechanisms.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not specify any IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119.xml'?> -->

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4541.xml'?>

      <reference anchor="uli">
        <front>
          <title>LLC Proposal for 802.15.4</title>

          <author surname="Pat Kinney">
            <organization>"IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>https://mentor.ieee.org/802.15/dcn/15/15-15-0521-01-wng0-llc-proposal-for-802-15-4.pptx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="Nov" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="mc-ack-mux">
        <front>
          <title>Multiplexing of Acknowledgements for Multicast
          Transmission</title>

          <author surname="Yusuke Tanaka et al.">
            <organization>"IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>https://mentor.ieee.org/802.11/dcn/15/11-15-0800-00-00ax-multiplexing-of-acknowledgements-for-multicast-transmission.pptx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="dot11">
        <front>
          <title>Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and
          Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications</title>

          <author surname="P802.11">
            <organization>"IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>http://standards.ieee.org/getieee802/download/802.11-2012.pdf
              (includes 802.11v amendment)</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="mc-props">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11 multicast properties</title>

          <author surname="Adrian Stephens">
            <organization>"IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>https://mentor.ieee.org/802.11/dcn/15/11-15-1161-02-0arc-802-11-multicast-properties.ppt</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="arpsponge">
        <front>
          <title>Arp Sponge</title>

          <author surname="Arien Vijn, Steven Bakker">
            <organization>"AMS"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>https://ams-ix.net/downloads/arpsponge/3.12.2/arpsponge-3.12.2/arpsponge.txt</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="dot11-proxyarp">
        <front>
          <title>Proxy ARP in 802.11ax</title>

          <author surname="P802.11">
            <organization>"IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>https://mentor.ieee.org/802.11/dcn/15/11-15-1015-01-00ax-proxy-arp-in-802-11ax.pptx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="dot11aa">
        <front>
          <title>Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and
          Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications Amendment 2: MAC Enhancements
          for Robust Audio Video Streaming</title>

          <author surname="P802.11">
            <organization>"IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>http://standards.ieee.org/getieee802/download/802.11aa-2012.pdf</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="mc-prob-stmt">
        <front>
          <title>Multicast on 802.11</title>

          <author surname="Mikael Abrahamsson and Adrian Stephens">
            <organization>"IAB, IEEE 802 Wireless"</organization>

            <address>
              <uri>https://www.iab.org/wp-content/IAB-uploads/2013/01/multicast-problem-statement.pptx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <!--
        <reference anchor="dot15mc">
        <front>
        <title>IEEE 802.15.4 and ZigBee as Enabling Technologies</title>
        <author surname='Stefano Tennina et al.'>
        <organization>
        </organization>
        <address>
        <uri>https://www.iab.org/wp-content/IAB-uploads/2013/01/multicast-problem-statement.pptx</uri>
        </address>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        </reference>

<author surname='Stefano Tennina, Anis Koubaa, Roberta Daidone,
Mario Alves, et al.'>
Koubaa had first 'a' with caret
Mario had 'a' with accent
    -->
    </references>

    <!--

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>
This document stems from discussions with the following people,
in alphabetical order:
Warren Kumari.

</t>

</section>
  -->
  </back>
</rfc>
